hello everyone and welcome once again to
the legal Paulo alwah will we jam 60
minutes of thought provoking discussion
into a 30 minute show designed to inform
affect a fellow American citizens we are
co-hosts Tom Scott and Sarah nahin Dee
and today we are absolutely thrilled to
have with us as I guess once again mr.
John Kiriakou former CIA
counterterrorism officer and get it for
the US Senate Committee on Foreign
Relations whistleblower author and
activist did I forget anything day
adjoined know I once said that keeps me
pretty busy
I bet does it but I bet if that's what
welcome once again to our show John
thank you thanks for having me always
happy to be with you thank you for
coming back we had such a great show
with you last time we were looking for
you know having you on again so Thank
You Klaus and if I viewers remember last
last year we had you on the show we had
a great discussion between then and now
I noticed you've received the 2016 Sam
Adams Award for integrity and it doesn't
appear many people have received that
award can you explain that and tell our
view was about that award and what it
entails sure Sam Adams is not the
founding father Sam Adams this Sam Adams
was a senior CIA analyst in the 1960s
and early 1970s who was the first person
really the only person to warn the White
House that the Pentagon was lying about
its numbers of Vietnamese troops and
Vietcong troops that were fighting
against us in the war
the Pentagon for political reasons was
under reporting those numbers Sam was
Harvard educated he had advanced degrees
in statistics and he was confident in
his methodology of course history has
proven him right but he paid for it with
his career he was he was sort of shunted
off into a do-nothing position he ended
up
my name from the CIA in 1971 and then
died of a heart attack soon after he was
only about fifty years old
but many of his friends remained for
their careers in the agency and when
they finally retired and formed a group
called veteran intelligence
professionals for sanity they
established the Sam Adams Award for
integrity and intelligence it's been
given out about a dozen times I want it
last year sy Hersh won it this year a
couple of years ago it was given to Ed
Snowden so it's it's generally been
given to people who have advanced the
cause of truth and intelligence and who
have paid a price for doing that I was I
was humbled to receive it wow that's a
big deal congratulations
thank you I've got it I've got it in
this cabinet right here it's it's a it's
a candlestick is what it is because it's
supposed to signify bringing light into
the dark recesses of the intelligence
community how did you feel about that
and what was that like what was that
experience like to receive that award oh
I'll tell you when I got it I had just
gotten out of prison and so it was you
know prison does something to you
whether you like it or not whether you
whether you think that it's happening or
not it it wears you down into a little
nub and it doesn't matter if you think
you were right or righteous it doesn't
matter if you think that you were
screwed by the government it doesn't
matter if you think that you were set up
for political reasons you still come out
and most of society just looks at you as
a convicted criminal you're a convicted
felon so to be honored by my my
colleagues and my peers from the CIA the
FBI NSA homeland security NCIS it meant
a lot to me you know it reminded me that
I I did the right thing when I blew the
whistle on the CIA's torture program and
even though the price was high it was
the right thing to do
did it make it to make you feel like
what you did
wasn't in vain completely yeah you know
what there have been a couple of things
that made me conclude that what I did
was not in vain
you know the first thing was in December
of 2015 this was five weeks before I was
released from prison I called my wife
and I said hey how was your day
and she said my day was great I said
yeah why and she said because the Senate
torture report was released today and it
proved that everything you said was true
and that made me feel good I got out in
February of 2015 and then in August of
2015 the McCain fine stein amendment to
the National Defense Authorization Act
was passed which expressly banned
torture exactly the kinds of torture
techniques that we were using against
al-qaeda prisoners in 2002 and John
McCain said that I was the inspiration
for that amendment so that made it all
worthwhile
that's very nice recognized by it was it
was well who's devoted his you know
entire career to public service yes yes
it was validating so John this that this
is actually a ward from you appears then
so that that's that really a would from
management of high levels it was one
thing but from peers the people you work
with on a day-to-day basis that means a
hell of a lot more right yeah and I'll
tell you what else means a hell of a lot
more when I was incarcerated 16
different CIA officers came to visit me
in prison Wow now a lot of people didn't
come to visit me including relatives
because they were afraid of God knows
what
oh the government's gonna listen to my
phone the government's gonna read my
emails well the government's listening
to your phone read your emails anyway
these CIA people really took a risk a
real risk to come and see me but it was
a statement that they wanted to make and
I was very grateful for the gesture
another question to John I mean you know
since all this has happened you know
have you pursued
clearing your name otherwise the record
straight with with people in general I
mean as you said earlier people look at
you as a convicted felon I mean as a
convict basically most people don't
realize how the legal system operates it
has the stigma associated with it it
almost should have an award I mean you
look at nd you look at the welts doin
Christ I mean who else Paul Martin
Luther King I mean all have been to
prison and these are not notorious
criminals they're at the opposite end of
the spectrum right these are people who
should have been given a parade not
prison time like you what is your
approach have you if you try to do
anything to clear your name or to set
that record straight actually yeah I
have I've been very blessed with with
crazy strong support in the Greek
American community and two very wealthy
and well-known Greek American
businessmen hired a lobbying firm to
lobby President Obama on my behalf I
applied for a presidential pardon and it
was hard work but what we ended up doing
was we got a meeting with Vice President
Biden and we gave to him a letter signed
by 70 retired CIA NSA and FBI officers
asking the President to pardon me we had
a floor statement from my congressman
a letter from the man who wrote the law
that I was convicted of violating saying
that this is not why he wrote the law
and that I should never have been
charged in the first place and then we
found an op-ed from the Christian
Science Monitor from 1981 written by one
US Senator Joseph R Biden saying that
the law I was convicted of was
unconstitutional on its face and should
never have been passed and so we went to
see by me and he hemmed and hawed and
finally because he of his long
association with
two Greek businessmen agreed to argue my
case to President Obama and so the the
businessman went with Biden to the White
House two nights before the end of the
Obama administration they called me at
almost midnight when they came out of
the White House and and one of them said
John you would have been so proud of the
vice president he went to the mat for
you
he really argued your case and then
finally after about ten minutes the
president said guys I'm just not going
to do this it's either this guy or it's
Manning and Manning got 35 years now why
Chelsea Manning and I are mutually
exclusive I have no idea but Barack
Obama made a hard-and-fast decision that
he was not going to help me now I
probably don't have a chance of a pardon
under Donald Trump but I might you know
I've I've made some inroads into the
White House there used to be a lot of
Greek Americans in the White House
they've all either been fired or
indicted at this point so I don't have
the Greeks to rely on but I do have one
path into the White House that may help
me and in the meantime an incredibly
generous Republican congressman with
strong libertarian leanings has
voluntarily offered to to write a bill
that he would introduce in the House of
Representatives to be Co introduced in
the Senate by Rand Paul that would
vacate my conviction and reinstate my
federal pension now that's a real uphill
struggle but I have to try everything if
I don't I'll never forgive myself
III have to try everything Wow in this
epoch and this has to do with you
federal pension - I didn't I wasn't
aware of that yeah you know it's not
just the idea of having gone to prison
for for two years and then being on
parole for not parole but federal
probation for two years it's not just a
question of losing my right to vote and
losing
my gun and my Second Amendment rights
but I also lost my federal pension I had
20 years of proud service in the federal
government and so without that pension
I'm I'm gonna have to literally work
until the day I die
I I had seven hundred and seventy
thousand dollars saved in that pension
I'd like it back wow that seems very
unfair and very very much
extraordinarily harsh - well I had no
idea like Tom said that that's that was
connected and part of it yeah when I say
the price was high I mean the price was
literally high very high well you know
movie both you know Sarah and I and I
hope my view is a pulling for you to get
this get this done because that's a
little ridiculous it's legalized theft
it's legalized theft is what it is
exactly what it is you know I had a
legal dream team here in Washington Joe
I had 11 attorneys three different firms
major partners the Washington Post
called my called my attorneys legal
Titans and one of them told me recently
he said you know I knew that Obama
wasn't gonna pardon you because it was
as though we were asking Obama to say my
bad I shouldn't have I shouldn't have
prosecuted him I'll pardon him you know
sorry about that
well that that was never gonna happen
but he said you've been so clearly
wronged by our government you're gonna
get that part in one of these days it
may not be with this president it may
not even be with the next one but
eventually you're gonna get that pardon
I hopefully believe that that should
happen and it would be a great
miscarriage of justice if it didn't
happen thank you very much so I hope it
happens under this president thank you I
hope so too like I say I have one Avenue
into this White House and I I'm gonna
either try if we could to one thing I'm
not sure if our viewers have heard about
Thomas Drake jessalyn rate act like the
documentary I guess it was silenced the
film directed by James Fiona um
can you explain what's what the message
is in that and how your role in the role
of Thomas Drake and Jesslyn Wright AK
Sheila whole thing together
sure jessalyn react was one of my
attorneys she had been the director of
ethics in the Justice Department and in
the immediate aftermath of the 9/11
attacks when John Walker Lindh the
American Taliban was arrested he was
arrested on a weekend and so FBI agents
called the Justice Department from
Afghanistan jessalyn was on duty and she
answered the phone and they said we
caught an American what do we do and she
said the first thing you have to do is
read him his rights
right he has a constitutional right
against self-incrimination they did not
read him his rights and in fact he made
confessions to criminal acts well a few
days later when the Attorney General
announced his arrest the Attorney
General specifically said he had been
read his rights and he waived them that
was a lie
so jessalyn went through the chain of
command to lodge a complaint she was
told to keep her mouth shut and instead
she went to the press when she went to
the press she was fired from the Justice
Department but worse than that the
Justice Department filed a complaint
against her with the District of
Columbia Bar Association to try to keep
her from ever working as an attorney
again and worse than that they put her
on the no-fly list as a terrorist
sympathizer in fact all she ever tried
to do was to protect the constitutional
rights of an American citizen she wasn't
taking a position on John Walker Lindh
politics
she was just treating him like any other
American in trouble now Tom Drake Tom
was a senior executive at NSA the
National Security Agency and Tom
stumbled on to this program called
thinthread where where Michael Hayden
who at the time was the director of NSA
had authorized a program to spy on
American citizens now this is clearly
unconstitutional and besides being
unconstitution
it's a violation of the NSA Charter
which specifically forbids it from
spying on American citizens Tom went
through his chain of command he went to
the Inspector General was told to mind
his own business he went to the general
counsel was told the same thing he went
to the DoD inspector general because NSA
is a DoD agency DoD actually destroyed
the evidence that Tom brought out with
him finally he went to the Congressional
Oversight Committee he went to the house
permanent Select Committee on
Intelligence and reported this now this
is the very definition of waste fraud
abuse and illegality and instead what
happened was the FBI charged Tom with
nine felonies including seven counts of
espionage well he hadn't committed
espionage obviously he was working for
the public good NSA was in violation of
the law DoD inspector general was in
violation of the law the case against
him ended up falling apart and all of
those felonies were dismissed but not
before he cashed in his pension in order
to pay his lawyer of bills he was
arrested and fingerprinted and booked
and finally released his wife left him
because she was an NSA employee and the
FBI said we're arresting your husband
this morning you're either with us or
you're with him she chose to be with the
FBI and now here he is a national hero
and the only work he can get is to work
as a clerk in an Apple store in Bethesda
Maryland
so Jim spean is a is an Academy Award
nominated documentary filmmaker when I
was arrested he asked through jesselyn
Radack
if he could film me for the year leading
up to my trial against my better
judgment at the time and against the
wishes of my entire legal team I agreed
and I'm glad that I did Jim really was
able to tell the story not just of my
case but of jessalyn case and Tom's case
and the unconstitutionality of so many
of the different things that our
government does in the in the false name
of national security we were all I'm
nominated for an Emmy Award last year
which was like a bizarro kind of weird
experience but here we are three people
have been charged with a variety of
national security crimes and none of us
had committed national security crimes
thank God none of us had been convicted
of national security crimes and we found
ourselves at the any Awards last year to
you you know Jim's beyond I owe him a
great deal he was he was really the only
one who was able to get get our story
out there for the American public and in
fact the documentary has been so
successful I think it's still on Netflix
Amazon and iTunes it's called silenced
Wow yeah do you have any idea I mean
these stories are you know incredible
and an unbelievable two people who just
don't understand that these kinds of
things happen and happen a lot in our
legal system what I mean do you think
that this has been happening for four
decades and from the beginning of this
country I mean this is coming and we
don't know I mean no no no it's been
happening since September 11th
everything changed on September 11th and
not for the better you know so many
people were so more farsighted than I
was because I believe that once we
defeated al-qaeda we would get our
September 10th country back and that
just wasn't the case at all there were
others in the national security
structure at the National Security
Council CIA NSA FBI Homeland Security
who decided that no this this 9/11
attack this was a game changer that they
were going to be able to do anything
they wanted and it didn't matter if they
didn't have a warrant it didn't matter
if they didn't have they didn't have
legal cause to for example intercept
every email that every American rights
or to intercept and put in a database
every telephone call every text message
that every American ever makes they have
enough storage space between what would
they have in a facility in Utah and a
new facility there building outside of
Fort Detrick Maryland they have enough
storage space to hold this information
for 500 years well that's not what the
Constitution says they can do
so the rest of us you know as Americans
we have to stand up and we have to say
this is wrong it's illegal and and we're
not going to allow it do you think yours
will ever go back to one surveillance
state or not obviously once something
like 9/11 happens you can never you can
never go backwards but do you ever think
that we will retract a little bit and
and not be as much of a you know big
brother kind of able to dull it a little
bit and the only reason I say that is
thanks to the revelations of event
Snowden
Congress has just now begun to act on
some of these mass surveillance issues
last year for example in the house and
this originated in something called the
freedom caucus and the House of
Representatives which is it's a
Republican caucus on the house side but
it's very libertarian in its leanings
they were the first ones to stand up for
example to section 7 20 of the National
Security Act allowing warrantless
wiretapping they were the first ones to
stand up and say that there ought to be
a sunset provision to to the Patriot Act
and by god there ought to be a sunset
provision to the Patriot Act the Patriot
Act should have to be renewed every
single year because times change
technology changes and public weal
changes and I for one don't want my
government spying on me or on anybody
else not without probable cause and not
without a warrant
which is what the Constitution calls for
yeah we we write about the USA patriot
act in our book and you know we refer to
the government's knee-jerk reaction
after the CAF has already left the pen
exactly right and the USA PATRIOT Act
has militarized further militarized
average police it's enabled more spying
on him gets done everything that it was
intended not to do and that's how laws
that are passed recently since 9/11 as
you say have become misused I mean the
intent the USA PATRIOT Act the all
there's a few we write about in our book
but but inevitably you know these these
laws further infringe of
specifically 4th and 5th amendment
rights as you just said and it's in its
and is getting worse they absolutely do
and it is getting worse I read recently
that the Ohio State University campus
police right the campus police for an
American College recently took delivery
of a tank for what reason what in the
world is the Ohio State University
Police Department going to use with a
tank tanks are for killing people is
that what they're going to do with it I
doubt it so they shouldn't have that
tank you know I read something
fascinating a week or two ago to you
know we've we've had somewhere in the
neighborhood of 1,100 police killings
into in 2017 this is the police shooting
innocent people 1107 according to the
American Civil Liberties Union the
conclusion the reason that this has
happened according to the ACLU is that
the average American Police Department
spends 90% of its time on shooting
practicing shooting and different
tactics and 10% of its time on
negotiation training conversely in the
UK there were 10 police shootings last
year now this is this is a country with
the same you know population as
California roughly 10 police shootings
but they spend 70 percent of their
training time on negotiations and only
30 percent on shooting there's something
for us to learn there yeah you know the
whole thing with this this the police
and the mentality in this country it
does almost like a ratcheting effect you
know the police become more aggressive
right so people are less a more afraid
of the police right so they become more
more intimidated so they're more likely
to react right and maybe even like all
these police shooting shootings of the
police themselves which makes the police
more irritable and more trigger-happy
which makes the people more afraid so
you get this constant well the whole
thing just explodes and I think that's
what we
seeing today right i mean how many
police police shootings but the
shootings of the police themselves and
you know it's not condone it I don't I
don't condone it whatsoever but
certainly it's yeah I agree with you I
agree with you but now we've got the
point where we have communities in this
country that see the police as an
occupation force because they're all in
black with with body armor and Kevlar
they have advanced weapons I mean what
are you supposed to conclude they're out
to kill people that's what that's what
Americans think now I mean especially if
you're certain races and and people that
are targeted I don't blame people for
being scared of the place I mean it it's
it is something to be feared I agree but
there's feel I'm afraid of the police
yeah yeah I hate to say I kind of am too
yeah I am too and and there's fear on
both sides and it's warranted given the
fabula
you know they carry guns and a lot of
Americans carry guns and and guns are
made for one purpose and one purpose
only and they're made to kill people
exactly that's it they're made to kill
people so it's it's understandable that
it shouldn't be happening and it
shouldn't be happening the way it's
happening and I hope that you know all
these stories and all the information
about the unnecessary and and brutal and
you know police killings for no reason I
mean I hope that that will make police
departments change how they operate you
know I think that the only thing that's
going to make police departments change
is police prosecutions when police
departments realize that there is a
price to pay
when you shoot a man in the back for
example who's running away from you
after a traffic dispute or this terrible
incident we had in Minnesota a couple of
weeks ago where a woman called 9-1-1
because she heard somebody being beaten
in the alley behind her house the
policeman pulls up she
out of her house to talk to the
policeman he rolls down the window of
his cruiser and shoots her point-blank
range and kills her and then the
district attorney said that he doesn't
think that he has enough evidence to
charge this cop in court well they're
not gonna ever learn their lessons
unless there's fallout legal fallout you
can't just kill people with impunity
at least you shouldn't be able to kill
people with impunity there should be no
blanket immunity right I mean people
they need to be prosecuted if you kill
somebody for no reason that was storming
we do have a thing called involuntary
manslaughter in this country so you
don't charge it and prosecute it yeah
like Sara says there should be no
blanket immunity for police lawyers
judges no blanket immunity whatsoever
and one thing I can tell you is I would
never call the police for anything I
mean somebody could have a gun to my
head I would still not call the police
because then just to me it escalates the
situation I really can't justify it I'm
not him Sean I mean this is always a
great conversation with you but I have
we have two questions I hope we can get
these questions answered I love them so
from this point forward right now I'm
quoting you on your website from this
point forward I know my mission but
change can you expound on that what
would you like to do what would you like
to see happen you know what my wife said
something when I was first arrested she
said if they thought that this would
silence you they don't know you at all
and she was right you know I I like to
think that I'm well-known enough or
notorious enough in this country that I
have a soapbox I've got a daily radio
show in Washington DC on 105.5 FM I have
a weekly column in reader supported news
I'm on the on the news shows all the
time CNN Fox MSNBC people listen to what
I have to say and I have a lot to say on
issues like prison reform and sentencing
reform and and respect for the
Constitution of the United States and so
I'm going to keep talking until they're
sick and tired of hearing it
and they either do something or they
stop inviting me onto these shows all
right water that they they keep but
sorry I hope that they keep inviting you
on the shows that they keep it affects
effectuates a change I hope so I hope so
so far so good
knock on wood Sarah is there anything
else you'd like to ask John I mean we're
pretty close this the only thing I have
is you know John what would you like to
see change or happen with the legal
system and what will you say to other
people who've never experienced that
system - the way you haven't warned them
about it I think I'd like to say two
things first what we need and second
what I would say what we need is to do
away with mandatory minimum sentencing
when one out of every four black men in
this country one out of every four
imagine that is either on parole on
probation or incarcerated in either jail
or prison we have a problem well when
one out of every two black men has spent
time in jail or prison that's a problem
when one out of every nine adults I mean
walk down the street how many people do
you see on the street one out of every
nine adults has a felony conviction you
have a problem we need to do something
about charge stacking about overcharging
about venue shopping we need to do
something about about prosecutorial
discretion which really is just ganging
up on somebody whose politics you don't
like in many cases the problem is in the
Justice Department something has to be
done there the advice that I would give
and I cannot be any more crystal clear
than what I'm going to say right now
do not ever under any circumstances talk
to a cop or talk to the FBI and I mean
especially the FBI because they will lie
they will cheat they will twist your
words they will take them out of context
and they'll
use them against you and they'll charge
you with the felony of making a false
statement you cannot trust the FBI
I've told ed Snowden Asst I've told
Julian Assange and I'm telling every
American who is watching this today
don't talk to the FBI well very strong
words and advice thank you John
thanks for having me it's always a
pleasure to see both of you yeah thanks
John we wish you the best this year keep
up the good work keep doing what you're
doing yeah we can't have you on again
and hear about what the what the latest
update is fantastic
and in the meantime I hope to see you at
the libertarian convention that would be
way before law to a job yeah all right
Hey yeah